<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funeral sermon on the decease of the Reverend Mr. Richard Mayo late minister of the gospel in London, who died the 8th of September, 1695 / by Nathanael Taylor.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Nathanael, d. 1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T543</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11964022</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11964022</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 829:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funeral sermon on the decease of the Reverend Mr. Richard Mayo late minister of the gospel in London, who died the 8th of September, 1695 / by Nathanael Taylor.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Nathanael, d. 1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Cockerill, senr and junr ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mayo, Richard, 1631?-1695.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, V, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51645:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51645:1"/>
            <p>A FUNERAL SERMON ON THE DECEASE Of the Reverend <hi rend="blackletterType">Mr. Richard Mayo,</hi> Late Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>London.</hi> Who Died the 8th of <hi>September,</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>By <hi>NATHANAEL TAYLOR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Cockerill,</hi> Sen<hi rend="sup">r</hi> and Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market.</hi> M DC XCV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51645:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51645:2"/>
            <head>TO That part of the Church of Chriſt in <hi>London,</hi> of which the Reverend Mr. <hi>RICHARD MAYO</hi> was lately Paſtor.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved in our Lord;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here preſent you with the following Sermon, which I hope, will meet with a kind and favourable Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from <hi>You.</hi> Indeed a ſtately Monument ſhewing the Excellency of the Work-man that <hi>erected</hi> it, as well as of him that is <hi>encloſed</hi> in it, is neceſſary to invite and gratify the curioſity of a <hi>Stranger.</hi> But any <hi>little</hi> thing, though ſo <hi>mean</hi> in it ſelf that it cannot challenge any regard upon its <hi>own account,</hi> yet is wont to have ſome value ſet upon it, becauſe 'tis <hi>the Memorial of a Departed Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Relation to you wherein both of us ſtood; the entire Affection you ſo juſtly had for <hi>him;</hi> the great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs you have ſhewn <hi>me</hi> for ſo many Years, together with the <hi>Additional</hi> one of ſo <hi>unanimouſly</hi> fiixing me in his room ſince his Deceaſe, do not only <hi>juſtify,</hi> but alſo <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> this my preſent Dedication.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51645:3"/>
            <p>I ſhall now more than ever need your Remembrance of me at the Throne of Grace, in order to the diſcharge of the great Truſt committed to me with Faithfulneſs and Succeſs, ſo that none of you may want a <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> nor I one of <hi>Rejoycing in the preſence of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt at his coming;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2.19.</note> which ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo be the daily Prayer and faithful Endeavour of him, who is on many accounts, with great Sincerity and Affection</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours to ſerve You In the Work of the Goſpel.</hi> Nathanael Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51645:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 COR. V. 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>We are confident, I ſay, and willing rather to be abſent from the body, and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN that Prophecy of our Bleſſed Saviour, recorded by the Evangeliſt,
<note place="margin">Luke 17.34, 36.</note> concerning ſome black and terrible Day, which ſome underſtand of the approaching ruin of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> State, and others apply to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the World; among other things we are told, That <hi>two Men</hi> ſhall be <hi>in the ſame field;</hi> two Perſons <hi>in one</hi> and the ſame <hi>bed, the one ſhall be taken, the other ſhall be left.</hi> Somewhat like this the Sovereign diſcriminating Providence of God hath lately done among you. Not long ſince <hi>Two</hi> Perſons were working in this part of God's Field: A few days ago there were <hi>Two</hi> that were wont to ſtand in the ſame Pulpit; the <hi>unprofitable</hi> Servant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is <hi>left,</hi> but Alas! the <hi>very Valuable</hi> one is <hi>taken.</hi> The firſt remarkable ſtroke that was given him, was <hi>in this very Place,</hi> and in the midſt of his Work; and the change that it made in <hi>his</hi> Countenance, and thereupon in many of <hi>yours,</hi> you cannot but remember. Death pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued the Blow that made the ſtrong and fruitful Tree to ſhake, till at laſt it fell to the Ground. And now, if like the Sons of the Prophets we ſhould ſeek our <hi>Elijah,</hi> it would be in vain; for he is <hi>Aſcended.</hi> 'Tis to no purpoſe to enquire for him at his own home, for he is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51645:4"/>abſent from his Family. 'Tis a vain thing to ſearch the houſes of any of his People for him, for he is abſent from his Flock. It would be loſt labour to ſeek him any where here below, for he is <hi>abſent from the Body</hi> too, and <hi>preſent with the Lord.</hi> Our time and pains will be far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter employed in ſeeking after ſome portion of the ſame Spirit that reſted on him, that ſo we who have ſo lately followed him to his Grave, and muſt ere long do ſo in another ſenſe, may follow him to Heaven too. For the hour of our deceaſe will come; whether we are <hi>willing</hi> or no, we alſo muſt ere long be <hi>abſent from the Body;</hi> and I wiſh our being <hi>preſent with the Lord,</hi> were but as ſure as that is. For could we but ſay upon good grounds with our A poſtle and his Brethren, that <hi>we are confident</hi> of this; we ſhould not ſtop there, but be able to go on to the end of the Text, and add, <hi>we are willing rather to be abſent</hi> from the one, and <hi>preſent</hi> with the other.</p>
            <p>In which words you have theſe three Parts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One of the true Notions of Death. 'Tis a being <hi>abſent from the Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What immediately follows upon it to a holy Soul. He ſhall thereupon be in Heaven; which the Apoſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes by one of the greateſt Privileges of it, being <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the Lord.</hi> 'Tis the Lord Jeſus Chriſt he here means. For of him is this word <hi>Lord</hi> uſed in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as peculiarly belonging to him. And in other parallel places the Apoſtle deſcribes the happineſs of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by our being <hi>with Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.23. 1 Theſſ. 4.17.</note> and <hi>being for ever with the Lord;</hi> where the Context plainly ſhews, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is meant; for 'tis that Lord that ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, and whom they that remain alive to that day ſhall be caught up to meet in the Air. And ſo our Saviour himſelf was wont to deſcribe Heaven. <hi>Where I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51645:4"/>am, there ſhall my ſervant be alſo.</hi> And,
<note place="margin">John 12.26. Chap. 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>I will receive you to my ſelf, that where I am, there ye may be alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The frame of his Spirit, and of other holy Men like him, in reference to Death on this account. <hi>We are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, I ſay, and willing rather to be abſent from the body, and be preſent with the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſay;</hi> Theſe words are not in the Original, but are well put in by our Tranſlators. The Apoſtle had ſaid this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>v.</hi> 6. And after the interpoſition of a ſhort Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, <hi>v.</hi> 7. For <hi>we walk by faith, and not by ſight,</hi> he here repeats it, leſt any ſhould ſuſpect that theſe great words had haſtily dropp'd from him. He intimates hereby that he had well-weigh'd the Point, and that this was indeed the ſettled temper of his Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are confident; i. e.</hi> we are well aſſured of Heaven; or, we are full of holy Courage to venture on all dangers that lye in the way of our Duty, and are able to look even Death it ſelf in the face, without the leaſt degree of fear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are willing.</hi> We do acquieſce in and approve of,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as the word ſignifies. We are willing <hi>rather.</hi> We have a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inclination to continue in this Body; but yet this is over-ruled by Reaſon and Grace to that degree, that of the two we like this better, to lay down theſe our Earthly Tabernacles, as knowing the advantage we ſhall receive thereupon by being immediately introduced into the bleſſed Preſence of Chriſt above.</p>
            <p>From the words thus open'd, many Doctrines might be raiſed; but I ſhall confine my ſelf to theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>'Tis a moſt deſirable thing to a holy Soul to be preſent with Chriſt in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>'Tis poſſible for a holy Perſon to be willing to dye, rather than live any longer, that he may be with him there.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51645:5"/>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>'Tis a moſt deſirable thing to a holy Soul to be preſent with Chriſt in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to this Point, I ſhall ſhew you on what accounts it is ſo. Only I muſt premiſe, That my Text confines me to treat of our being with him only in that intermediate ſpace of time between the hour of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's Death, and the Day of the Reſurrection; being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with him while we are <hi>abſent from the Body.</hi> For tho indeed we ſhall be with him to all Eternity, yet we ſhall behold him in other kind of Circumſtances as to <hi>ſome</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; when <hi>the end</hi> of all things is come, his interceſſion is over,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>the Kingdom ſhall be delivered up to the Father, and the Son himſelf ſhall be ſubject to him, that God may be all in all.</hi> I am therefore to diſcourſe of the preſence of holy Souls with Chriſt above to <hi>the end of the World.</hi> And how very deſirable that is to them, will appear by a threefold conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Perſon they ſhall then be preſent with.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The State he is in, and what ſhall be manifeſted concerning him there.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Circumſtances which they themſelves ſhall then be in.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Perſon</hi> they ſhall then be preſent with; our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. For conſider how glorious he is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, how exceeding gracious he hath been to them, and how great a one in their thoughts. He is the King of kings, and the Lord of lords, the firſt and the laſt, the brightneſs of his Father's Glory, and the expreſs image of his Perſon, by and for whom all things were created; and who upholds all things by the word of his Power. Their Prophet, Prieſt and King; their Sacrifice, Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciler and Advocate; their Peace and Hope; their Life
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51645:5"/>and Head; their way to the Father, the Saviour, the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd and Biſhop of their Souls; made to them of God, Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption. Without whom they could do nothing, through whoſe ſtrengthning of them they could do all things. From whom they have received all habitual, and all ſupplies of actual Grace, and Peace, and Comfort in every time of need: Through whom their Sins are pardoned, their Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions conquer'd, their Fears ſcatter'd, their Sorrows re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, their Souls quickned, their Trials ſanctified, and who in all their wandrings through the howling Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath been a Pillar of <hi>Cloud</hi> to defend them from the ſcorching heat of the Day, and of <hi>Fire</hi> to guide them through the darkneſs of the Night. The bleſſed Jeſus on whom they have believed, having committed their Souls to him, and laid the whole weight and ſtreſs of their Salvation upon him; whom they love more than their neareſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, or their own Lives; in whom they rejoice, having no confidence in the Fleſh; whom they have ſerved, to whom they have lived; Fellowſhip and Communion with whom they have breathed after, and a little taſte whereof hath been ſweeter to them than Wine; who is precious to their Souls, the chiefeſt of ten thouſands, fairer than all the Children of Men, whoſe very name hath carried with it the ſavour of Life. What would not a diſconſolate Widow give to enjoy again the ſweet converſe of a Husband that was the delight of her Eyes! And a mournful People to ſee and hear again their dear and juſtly-beloved Paſtor! Oh what raviſhing tranſports will be in the Faithful, when they ſhall be introduced into the preſence of that Jeſus who ſtood in the <hi>ſame Relations,</hi> and filled them up far better than any meer Creature was ever capable of; eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering they ſhall ſee him not in a low condition, but in ſuch circumſtances as they deſire to behold him in. Which leads to,</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51645:6"/>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſtate</hi> that Chriſt is in above, and the <hi>manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of him there. He is there without that Veil, and thoſe Eclipſes which were here cauſed by his ſinleſs Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities in the Days of his fleſh. For conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The glory of his <hi>humane Nature</hi> above. That Body of his which endured Hunger, Thirſt, and Wearineſs, was Spit on, Buffeted, Scourged, and Broken for them, lifted up on the Croſs, and caſt into the Grave, is now made Immortal and Spiritual; and differs as much from what it once was, as a Diamond when it is rough, and after it hath paſt through the Hands of the skilful Artiſt, ſetting off its native Beauty and Luſtre to the greateſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. It now out ſhines the Sun in his Meridian bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: For ſo ſhall the Bodies of his Saints do at the laſt Day, which yet muſt be much inferior to his, he being the Exemplar and Patern to which theirs ſhall be conform'd, but yet fall far ſhort of it, that in all things he may have the <hi>pre-eminence.</hi> All the Members, Senſes, and Faculties of it are every way ſuited to all the purpoſes and pleaſures of his Holy Soul: And all the Powers of that Soul of his exquiſitely fitted for that noble Work and high Honour to which his Father hath advanced him; and invigorated by the conſtant and unlimited influences of the indwelling Deity pouring it ſelf into, and in a moſt ineffable manner diſcovering its own glorious Excellencies through the Man Chriſt Jeſus, to the everlaſting Admiration of all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The manifeſtation of his <hi>Deity, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with the Father, and myſtical union with his Brethren.</hi> His God-head lay hid and obſcured for a ſeaſon when he emptied himſelf, making himſelf of no Reputation, taking on him the form of a Servant, and enduring the puniſhment of a Slave. The ſpeedy diſcovery of it therefore he prays for when he was going out of the World; at leaſt this is one thing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51645:6"/>intended in thoſe words, <hi>And now, O Father,
<note place="margin">John 17.5.</note> glorify thou me with thine own ſelf with the glory which I had with thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World was.</hi> For this glory he had with the Father from all Eternity, to be with him in the form of God. And 'tis as if he had ſaid, this hath now been hid by the poverty of my life for many Years, and will further be ſo by my ſpeedy ſuffering ſo ſhameful a Death. But O Father, make it fully known that I am not what the moſt have hitherto judged me to be, a meer Man, but truly and really God, even the ſame God with thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>And he himſelf told his Diſciples,
<note place="margin">John 14.20.</note> 
               <hi>In that day ye ſhall know that I am in the Father; and you in me, and I in you.</hi> Some underſtand it of the day of his Reſurrection; others, of the time when the Holy Ghoſt was poured forth. But how ſmall a portion of theſe deep Myſteries did they then know, in compariſon of what they in Heaven underſtand, where Knowledge is perfect? The better underſtanding of them is reſerved for us as one of the Priviledges of the State a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove: And it were well Men were willing to wait for it till they come thither, and would forbear reaching after this Fruit which hangs too high for them in their preſent State, till they <hi>ſtrain</hi> themſelves, and it may be tumble into the Ditch. Theſe great things of God partly through the craft of Satan and his Inſtruments, and partly through the darkneſs and unbelief of their own Spirits, the beſt are ſometimes apt to ſtagger at; but yet becauſe they are laid down in the Scriptures, they humbly adore and receive with the Obedience of Faith. It cannot but ſhed a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pleaſure throughout the Souls of the Bleſſed, when they ſhall ſee them diſplayed in ſuch an illuſtrious manner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, as never more to have an uneaſy thought, like a Thorn in their Minds, about them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His glorious work of <hi>Redemption</hi> ſhall then be much better underſtood. The breadth and length, the depth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51645:7"/>and height of the love of Chriſt, and the glory of Divine Wiſdom, Power, Holineſs, Juſtice, Goodneſs, Mercy and Grace manifeſted herein, is that which they are daily ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of; their Souls do live upon, and are refreſhed by. <hi>Theſe things we ſee</hi> now <hi>through a glaſs darkly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12. Ver. 9.</note> What things doth the Apoſtle mean? The fame things that they <hi>did prophecy about;</hi> viz. <hi>Chriſt and him crucified.</hi> We ſee theſe now as a Man doth thoſe objects that are at a great diſtance through a Perſpective-glaſs, which he hath but a ſmall glimpſe of.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> They are obſcure in a great meaſure to us, as Truths wrapt up in a Riddle: But then we ſhall know them <hi>face to face,</hi> have ſuch a knowledge of them as two perſons have of one another that ſteadily view each others faces: <hi>Now we know but in part, but then ſhall we know even as alſo we are known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The views they ſhall have of his <hi>Interceſſion</hi> for all Saints.
<note place="margin">Heb. 5.5.</note> This is a part of that Honour and Office to which the Father hath called, and thereby <hi>glorified</hi> him. To per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how near an acceſs he hath to God, being now within the Veil, how high his deſigns are, how powerful his claims, how acceptable his ſuit, how great an intereſt he hath in him, how faithfully he doth improve it in the behalf of his and their Brethren, how fervently he doth plead their cauſe, recommend their perſons and ſervices, procure their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed pardon and continual ſupplies of Grace and Strength for the carrying them through the ſame or the like temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, doubts, diſtreſſes and dangers, wherewith they themſelves had been exerciſed here below; and how effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he takes care of their eternal Salvation. The beholding all this cannot but be highly grateful and pleaſing to thoſe Holy departed Souls, that have ſo high a concern for the glory of God, and the welfare of their Brethren that are left behind them, expoſed to ſo many ſtorms which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have ſo happily eſcaped. Eſpecially conſidering this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51645:7"/>further, that the tenderneſs of Chriſt towards their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren which they there behold, cannot but create in them a quick and lively Senſe of the incomparable Kindneſs and Compaſſion which he formerly ſhewed to themſelves when in the ſame ſtraits. In what he doth for them, as in a Glaſs, they ſee how near they lay to his Heart, and in what a manner he appeared in the preſence of God for them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That univerſal <hi>Kingly Power</hi> that he is inſtated in. This is a part of that Glory that Chriſt means in that Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his, that runs in a very peculiar ſtrain: <hi>Father I will,
<note place="margin">John 17.24.</note> that they alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory which thou haſt given me, for thou lovedſt me before the foundation of the World.</hi> The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting upon his moſt endearing Relation to him, <hi>Father;</hi> the manner of expreſſion, <hi>I will;</hi> and the enforcing it with the conſideration of the everlaſting Love that he bare to him, ſhew how much the Heart of Chriſt was ſet upon this matter. The views of Chriſt, as lifted up on the Croſs, have been unſpeakably refreſhing to them here below; How much more will the views of him be ſo upon the Throne above,
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.21, 22.</note> where he is exalted <hi>far above all principality and power, and might and dominion, and every name that is named not only in this world, but in that which is to come, all things being put under his feet?</hi> It cannot but be ſo, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how fit and reaſonable a conſtitution this is, how honourable to him, that 'tis his reward for what he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured on their account, and that of the reſt of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; that he is now in a condition to vindicate his own Honour againſt all thoſe whom they formerly ſaw to the great grief of their Souls reproaching, deſpiſing, hating and oppoſing of him; that he is able to ſave his whole Church, and fulfil all the promiſes made unto her. He is in ſuch Circumſtances that he can give <hi>Eternal life to all that
<note place="margin">John 17.3.</note>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51645:8"/>the Father gave him, for he hath a power over all Fleſh given him</hi> to that end.
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.22, 23.</note> And he <hi>is head over all things unto his Church, which is his body, the fulneſs of him that filleth all in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. His entire <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> and Devotedneſs to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. How amiable a ſight is an eminent Saint on Earth, on whom the Divine Image is ſtamp'd, the whole tenor of whoſe life ſhews the ſincerity of his aims for God, and the purity of his affections to him? Such a one is a very valuable thing, like a ſmall but exact Medal of a great King; and 'tis Pity there ſhould be the ſame reaſon to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance the worth of the one as of the other, the great ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of them. And yet there's no ſuch perſon to be found on Earth but hath his Blemiſhes, and ſometimes takes a wrong Step or two; as the moſt exact compaſs in ſome places hath its <hi>Variations.</hi> What then will it be to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our Lord Jeſus, the brighteſt and moſt perfect Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar of Fidelity to, and Zeal for his Father's Intereſt and Honour! For he not only leads a life of Glory above, but a life of Service too:
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>In that he liveth, he liveth unto God.</hi> Both as Prieſt and King he faithfully manageth all things with due Reſpects to his Father's Will and Glory, and goes on continually beating down every perſon and thing that exalt themſelves againſt him, till all being brought into an entire ſubjection to him, the Kingdom be reſign'd up into his Father's Hands.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>excellent State of all that are preſent with him,</hi> Angels and departed Saints. For in the ſame Firmament where the Sun is, theſe Stars are fixed and ſhine with a diſtinct Glory. His Government is acceptable, and all his Subjects eaſy and orderly; noble and holy, numerous and inexpreſſibly happy. The place where they are, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtyles it,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>The moſt excellent Glory.</hi> Who can tell what noble Creatures the good Angels are, or how many
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51645:8"/>Myriads of them there be? Or give us a clear Comment on St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, where he makes a diſtinction between <hi>principalities and powers, and thrones and dominions?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.16.</note> Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome of them are ſubordinated to others is not ſo clear. But ſure we are they are all ſubjected to Chriſt, and there is not the leaſt ſhadow of Confuſion or Diſorder among them: The Spirits of juſt Men there are perfect, and their number daily encreaſing: None there hath ſo much as a Thorn in his Foot, a Cloud on his Face, a Tear in his Eye, or a Spot on his Soul. There's neither Pride nor Envy, Jealouſy nor Strife, Weakneſs or Folly, to render them uneaſy to themſelves or each other; they are like flaming Tapers in a Branch of burniſhed Gold, which ſo mingle their ſeveral Lights, that at a diſtance they ſeem to be but one, though indeed they are many. They live in glorious Light, entire Love, and perfect Harmony, and ſuch a fulneſs of Joy, that there is no room for any Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to creep in among them. Now if the Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> when ſhe ſaw the Glory and Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Statelineſs and Magnificence of his Buildings, and the Riches, Beauty, and Order of his Court, was wrapt up into ſuch an Admiration of him, and ſaid,
<note place="margin">1 King 10.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Happy are theſe thy ſervants which ſtand continually before thee:</hi> Who can imagine the Extaſies of a holy Soul when brought into the preſence of Chriſt, the Glory of whoſe Court and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth more exceed his, than the place where Chriſt is is higher than that Throne on which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſate.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The univerſal <hi>Adoration</hi> given to Chriſt by all the Hoſt of Heaven. They all ſay, with a <hi>loud voice,
<note place="margin">Rev. 5.12, 13.</note> Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain, to receive power, and riches, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and ſtrength, and honour and glory, and bleſſing.</hi> And they actually give him what they acknowledge him to be ſo worthy of; for they add <hi>bleſſing, and honour, and glory, and power be unto him that ſitteth upon the throne, and unto
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51645:9"/>the Lamb for ever and ever.</hi> O the pleaſant melodious found of this Song (ſung by ſo many ſweet Voices in the heavenly Choir) to a holy Soul that ſees ſo much of Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and Glory in Chriſt, and is ſo ſenſible of the ſtraitneſs of his own narrow Spirit, that he unfeignedly wiſhes that wherever there is a Heart, he had a Throne, and is daily grieved here below to behold him ſo deſpiſed and rejected of Men, that know neither him nor their own Mercies!</p>
            <p>So much for that ſecond Conſideration. The State that Chriſt is in, and what ſhall be manifeſted concerning him above. To this I muſt add,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Circumſtances which holy Men themſelves</hi> ſhall be in when preſent with him.</p>
            <p>And here conſider 1. what lies in the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>abſent from the body, i. e.</hi> the <hi>preſent</hi> one. Not that it can be the happineſs of a Soul to be eternally unclothed of <hi>any body at all,</hi> and commence a purely naked Spirit; nor the matter of a regular deſire. Departed Spirits retain an inclination to their old <hi>Collegue,</hi> and the being reunited to it when 'tis ſo much improved, as it ſhall be at the laſt day, will be an additional bliſs to what they now enjoy. But yet a removal from this Body <hi>as now it is,</hi> where the bright Sword is ſo much impaired by the ruſty Sheath wherein 'tis lodged, may juſtly be eſteemed no ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. For what vile things are theſe Bodies of ours <hi>at preſent?</hi> 'Tis an humbling deſcription given of us while we are in this World,
<note place="margin">Job 4.19. Ch. 17.14.</note> that we <hi>dwell in houſes of clay whoſe foundation is in the duſt:</hi> that <hi>corruption is our father, and the worm our mother and our ſiſter;</hi> and theſe unnatural Parents will ere long devour their Children. How many inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences and evils are we ſubject to while we are lodged in theſe ſorry Tenements? <hi>Sleep,</hi> which is the reſt of our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51645:9"/>Nature, is the Image of Death, and interrupts our moſt noble Thoughts and Deſigns. 'Tis to life, like long and frequently returning <hi>Parentheſes</hi> in an Author, that <hi>ſuſpend his ſenſe,</hi> and mar the beauty of his Stile. The ſeveral Creatures that we live upon, <hi>revenge themſelves</hi> upon us; for much of our precious time is eaten up while we feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. And he that never found any ones Table to be a ſnare to him, is a perfect Man indeed. <hi>Recreations,</hi> tho in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and neceſſary, are a great Diverſion from the main buſineſs of Life, and hinder the Rational and Divine Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and Improvement of the Faculties of our Souls. How doth the providing Accommodations for theſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of ours engroſs our Thoughts, take off the edge and vigour of our Affections from heavenly things, ſteal away our hearts from God, and the one thing neceſſary, and fill us with pale Fears and perplexing Cares, ſo that we neglect our Duty, or perform it with abundance of coldneſs, and a world of diſtraction? How much guilt do we contract? How many follies are we betrayed into out of an inordinate love of bodily Pleaſure, and a ſinful fear of bodily Pains?</p>
            <p>How many Sins are Men ſtrongly inclined to by their Conſtitution and Complection? We need to make but one viſit to a melancholy Perſon, and we ſhall preſently ſee what a fatal Enemy Bodily-Temper is to a Life of Grace and Peace? How often doth Sin enter in at our Ears, and our Eyes? The <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hath far more reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of being <hi>deceived by his Senſes,</hi> than the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> hath? How frequently do bodily Paſſions darken our Minds, and cloud our Judgments, and involve us in Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal as well as Speculative Errors? And the weakneſs and diſorders of the Fleſh cramp the forward motions of a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Spirit?</p>
            <p>What a multitude of tormenting Diſeaſes are they ſubject to, which ſhatter our Underſtandings, and bow
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51645:10"/>down our Spirits to a continual Meditation on our Miſery; are an Obſtruction to the preſent performance of Duty, as well as a Chaſtiſment for our former neglects; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us to ſtrong Temptations to impatience and fretting againſt Gods, jealouſies and hard thoughts of him. How many cruel methods of Cure are we forced to ſubmit to? How many Potions do we ſometimes ſwallow down, which are ſo very nauſeous, that they would make a man Sick, if they did not find him ſo? And when the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt is over, how much time and pains doth it coſt us to ſtop the <hi>Leaks,</hi> and piece up the ruins of the poor wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beaten Veſſel? All which too is but the rigging it out for a new Storm that will ariſe again in a few days. For the Sun doth not more certainly and more conſtantly run through the ſame <hi>Signs,</hi> than many paſs through the ſame Diſeaſes. And they who happily eſcape ſuch Calamities as theſe, ſhall have the rough Wind often blowing upon them from ſome other Corner, in this <hi>open</hi> State where we are ſo much expoſed every moment.</p>
            <p>'Tis no ſmall part of the Happineſs of departed Saints, that they are abſent from <hi>ſuch</hi> a Body as this is, which yet they know ſhall be reſtored to them with ſo great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage at the laſt day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider the happineſs of their <hi>Souls.</hi> They ſhall be perfectly conform'd to God's Image, and ſatisfied with his Likeneſs. They ſhall never any more groan as now they do, Wretched Creature that I am, who have ſo much of Corruption, and ſo little of Chriſt in me! In this World ſometimes they <hi>are ſick of love to him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.5.</note> but have oftner reaſon to be ſo for <hi>want</hi> of it. There they ſhall love him as they <hi>would,</hi> which they never could do before. They ſhall have no chilneſs on their Spirits, no coldneſs on their Hearts. Never more ſhall that doleful cry be heard,
<note place="margin">Cant. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>We ſought him whom our ſouls loved, but we found
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51645:10"/>him not.</hi> Now they have a ſmall glimpſe of him in an Ordinance, as a Man of a Star through a glaſs held in a ſhaking and trembling hand, which he juſt ſees and loſes. Now a Cloud is often drawn between him and them, but then they ſhall with a ſteady Eye always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his pleaſed and glorious Face. They ſup with him now, and how ſweet, but oh how ſhort is the Banquet! But then they ſhall always eat and drink with him at his Table, ſit with him on his Throne, as he ſat down on his Father's Throne; ſhall be Heirs together with him, and have a Kingdom appointed to each of them, as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath appointed one for him. By ſuch earthly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, becauſe we are not capable of underſtanding heavenly Language, doth the Scripture ſhadow forth to us their moſt intimate and delightful Converſe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him; and how in their reſpective Meaſures and Degrees they ſhall be partakers together with him of ſuch Bliſs and Glory, <hi>as eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor can it enter into our hearts to conceive.</hi> Now all theſe things being laid together, no wonder that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Souls are <hi>willing to be preſent with the Lord.</hi> One would think that all the true Lovers of Chriſt ſhould ſay, not as his Diſciples, <hi>Let us go away and die with him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 11.16.</note> but let us go away and <hi>live,</hi> and be for ever with him. And ſo they would, but that there's a Lion in the way; Death is the paſſage to him. They muſt be <hi>abſent from the Body,</hi> before they can get to him, a thing that few have a heart to deſire, tho our Apoſtle and his Brethren did ſo. Which brings me to the</p>
            <p n="2">II Point. <hi>'Tis poſſible for a holy Perſon to be willing to dye, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than live any longer, that he may be with Chriſt in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall endeavour to open this in theſe following Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51645:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51645:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51645:12"/>
            <p n="1">1. All ſincere Chriſtians are <hi>willing to be with Chriſt above.</hi> For they profeſs themſelves to be Pilgrims and Strangers on the Earth, and declare plainly by the Tenor of their Lives, that they ſeek another Country. Their Converſations and their Hearts are in Heaven, they have ſet their Affections upon, and ſeek after the <hi>things that are above,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.1, 2.</note> where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God. They love him more than life it ſelf, and can't bear the thoughts of being eternally at ſo great a diſtance from him. They have been drawn to him by that promiſe among others,
<note place="margin">John 12.26.</note> 
               <hi>Where I am, my ſervant alſo ſhall be;</hi> the fulfilling of it therefore cannot but be grateful to them. 'Tis the main buſineſs of their Lives to prepare for an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Abode with him, and Miniſtration before him in the holieſt of all. This is what they have in their eye, as the great end of their attendance on him in his Ordinances. And is it poſſible for them to be unwilling to enjoy what they are continually providing for? They <hi>hope</hi> for Heaven, and that cannot be without deſiring to be there, that they may have the neareſt Conjunction with him, and the fulleſt Enjoyment of him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All holy Souls are willing <hi>in the general</hi> to dye <hi>ſome time or other,</hi> that they may be with him. This follows from the foregoing particular. They know there is no other way but being abſent from the Body to get to him. This therefore doth ſo far reconcile them to Death, that they had rather <hi>on the whole</hi> ſubmit to its ſtroke, than to an eternal diſtance from him whom their Soul loveth. They fear the King of Terrors indeed, but they fear and abhor an everlaſting Separation from Chriſt a great deal more. Tho when it comes to the Point, many of them are afraid to dye, and ready to contradict all again; yet they would not for all this World, and the Glory of it live always, if they might, in their preſent State. And
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51645:12"/>this doth not flow from a ſullen and impatient humour. For,</p>
            <p n="3">3. A holy Soul's willingneſs to dye, proceeds <hi>from noble Principles.</hi> He is not like the men of this World, who when croſſed, in diſcontent, paſſion, and deſpair, madly wiſh for Death, and ſometimes ſinfully haſten it; which is not a deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be with Chriſt, but only to be out of their preſent Miſery. Not but that a ſincere Chriſtian may have thoſe ſhort-liv'd fits and pangs that are very unbecoming; but theſe are the ſinful Infirmities of the man, not the holy Groanings of the Saint within, which we are now ſpeaking of. The <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental fretting</hi> of a rich and generous Wine muſt be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht from its natural Ferment.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, indeed, a ſenſe of thoſe Miſeries that preſs ſo hard upon them, is a <hi>help</hi> to theſe deſires. Being <hi>burden'd,</hi> we groan after the heavenly Houſe.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.4.</note> But the true <hi>Springs</hi> of their willingneſs to depart, are ſuch as theſe: A certain Knowledge and ſerious Conſideration of the Happineſs of being with Chriſt, and how much better that is than to continue here. A new Nature that tends to the place whence it came. A Divine Faith; Love to Chriſt; ſome degree of a weanedneſs from, and deadneſs to this World, and a ſerious preparation for the next; ſome good hopes, through Grace, of Eternal Life; ſome taſte of the ſweetneſs of an imperfect fellowſhip with Chriſt here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and deſires of drinking more of this Water of Life at the Fountain-head. Theſe are the things that make theſe Doves be upon the wing, ready to fly away towards Heaven.</p>
            <p>But yet they are not too forward to be gone. For,</p>
            <p n="4">4. This willingneſs is <hi>duly regulated</hi> with an entire ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Divine Will. Tho they are in a cloſe and painful Confinement, yet they are not for breaking Priſon, but reſolve to wait till they are releaſed by Authority. They are not like an haſty Clock that out-runs time, and ſtrikes before the hour is come. Tho they are willing rather
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51645:13"/>to depart, yet they are contented to ſtay as long as God hath any Work and Service for them to do in this World; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the Preſence of Chriſt, when they are introduced into it, will make abundant amends for the delays and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of a few moments; and the more they do for him, the greater ſhall be their reward. But tho that be ſo very great; yet</p>
            <p n="5">5. There are <hi>many things that do check</hi> and abate theſe Inclinations of a holy Soul.</p>
            <p>A real deſire of being further ſerviceable to the intereſt of Chriſt in this World. This was the Apoſtle's caſe, who was willing to have his happineſs ſuſpended for a time, becauſe <hi>to abide in the fleſh was more needful</hi> for others.
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The weakneſs of their Faith, and love to Chriſt. Too great addictedneſs to this World. Immoderate love to near Relations, with ſome touches of a diſtruſt of Divine Providence, as tho God either would not, or could not take care of them and their Affairs, when we are gone.</p>
            <p>But the more common and powerful Obſtructions are theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A natural Fear of Death.</hi> Could they with a ſudden <hi>Spring</hi> leap over the Gulf, and in a moment be with Chriſt; Could they but as eaſily get up to the place where he is, as his three Diſciples to the top of that Mountain where he was transfigured; they would do it without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy or delay. But alas, the dark Valley muſt firſt be paſſed through, <hi>Death</hi> muſt firſt be endured by them; a fear of which the God of Nature hath inwrought into the very Frame and Conſtitution of Man, it being neceſſary in order to the good Government of this World. His own commands are enforced with the promiſes of a long Life, and the threatnings of a ſpeedy Death; which Sanction of his would loſe its edge and force, did not Men love the one, and dread the other. Were it not for this, the refined ſort
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51645:13"/>of Mankind would ſinfully neglect the Body, and never undergo all that Slavery which now they endure for its Preſervation. Upon every croſs accident men would lay violent hands on themſelves; at leaſt, on every ſore Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they would boldly cut the Cable that faſtens them to this wretched Shoar, and ſail away to the inviſible World, and this Earth be unpeopled, and much thinner of Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants than God hath deſign'd it ſhould be for a ſeaſon. The Magiſtrate would then always <hi>bear the Sword in vain,</hi> for no one would fear the edge of it. All places would be fill'd with Rapine and Blood; for he that deſpiſeth his own Life, is maſter of his Neighbour's almoſt whenever he pleaſeth. And holy Men would not have that opportunity for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and diſcovery of their Graces, as now they have, in conquering the Reluctancies of Nature, and laying down their heads to receive the fatal ſtroke with ſteddineſs and compoſure of Mind. So to do, is great indeed. For to endure tedious Sickneſs, and ſharp Pains, the rude Knocks, the ſtrong and repeated Blows that this Enemy gives to break aſunder Body and Soul, which are ſo ſtrongly faſtned together; to be caſt as a noiſome Lump into the Grave, there to crumble into Duſt, to be triumphed over by worms, and turned into corruption and rottenneſs; theſe are very formidable things. How doth this beat down the aſcending Flame, and hinder its riſe! It is hereupon with a Chriſtian, as with an affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Child that is in another Land, and deſirous to go home that he may be with his beloved Father. But there's a dangerous Sea to be firſt paſſed over, and therefore he often comes down to the Shoar, looks wiſhly over to the other ſide, and would be glad he was there. But when he ſees the ſwelling Billows, his heart miſgives him, and he hardly knows how to think of venturing and launching forth.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51645:14"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The want of Aſſurance.</hi> Many are ignorant, unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and negligent in the great work of Self-examination. Many have but very low degrees of grace; the hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God's Spirit on their hearts is in ſo very <hi>ſmall a Character</hi> that they are not able to read it. Too many are looſe and careleſs in their Walk. Not a few are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run with Melancholy, and have diſmal apprehenſions of their ſtate, tho a judicious Stander by may perceive the goodneſs of it; the dark ſide of the Lanthorn is towards themſelves, and tho others behold the Grace of God in them as a burning and a ſhining Light, yet the Perſons themſelves cannot diſcern it. And in this gloomy State they conclude if they ſhould dye, they ſhould be baniſht from the Preſence of Chriſt; and under theſe apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Death is ſuch a thing, as ſtrikes Terror and Confuſion into every corner of their Souls.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the things whereby the Soul of a ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is preſſed down, as the inferior Air is in the Judgment of Modern Philoſophers, by the incumbent weight of the ſuperior Air and Clouds; which as ſoon as 'tis in any degree unfetter'd from, by a ſpring that is natural to it ſelf, it flies up again. Which brings me to the</p>
            <p n="6">6. As <hi>the heavenly Life improves, ſo holy Souls get ground on the fears of Death, and are more willing</hi> to be gone, that they may be with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>As Grace and Peace are multiplied in their Souls, as theſe living Waters do encreaſe, they lift them higher and nearer towards Heaven. The young and tender Eagles are afraid to ſtir out of the Neſt, and try their fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Wings; but when they arrive to a greater ſtrength, they can mount upwards with a vigorous flight. When they are arrived at the ſame height and ſtature in Chriſt as <hi>Paul</hi> was; when they can ſay on as good grounds as he, <hi>To us to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gain;</hi> eſpecially at
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51645:14"/>ſome ſeaſons when their Hearts are liſted up into a heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Frame, and enlarged in ſweet Communion with God in Chriſt: They can long for Death, welcome it, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over it. When their near Relations and Friends ſtand round about their Sick-Beds very Sad and Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>they</hi> are the only chearful Perſons in the Room; they can die <hi>ſmiling,</hi> and ſpend their expiring Breath in Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujahs, that bear ſome reſemblance with thoſe they are to ſing for ever. Their laſt Speeches are like the grateful ſtroaks of a skilful Muſician when his Inſtrument is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt brought in Tune; a delightful <hi>Praeludium</hi> to the ſweet Melody that ſhall immediately ſucceed. Hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</p>
            <p n="7">7. That this is not <hi>a mark</hi> whereby to try the <hi>truth,</hi> ſo much as the <hi>ſtrength of our Grace.</hi> For though there be ſome true deſires in the Soul this way, yet they may be ſo born down by many things, that they are not eaſily diſcerni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; like Seed in the ground that may be rooted there, but yet hath not ſhot through the ſurface of the Earth, nor is it crowned with a beautiful Flower; or if it hath been ſo, yet may be covered by an extraordinary Snow, and be invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the preſent. All cannot attain to <hi>Paul</hi>'s Height and Spirit; the Children come behind the young Men, and the young Men themſelves fall ſhort of thoſe that are Fathers in Chriſt. Indeed no great meaſure of this can be attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but by great improvements in Grace, a long and cloſe walking with God, and contending with Fleſh and Blood that ſtrongly oppoſe and ſpeak contrary things.</p>
            <p>But yet to prevent Sloth, and rouze up our dull and ſluggiſh Hearts; I add,</p>
            <p n="8">8. That <hi>more of this Spirit ought diligently to be laboured after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall have occaſion briefly to urge this in the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Which I now haſten to.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51645:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Is Heaven <hi>deſirable to you under this notion</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our Apoſtle ſets it forth? It is amiable in your Eyes, as a place where you hope to be eaſed of all thoſe Afflictions that ſit ſo very uneaſy upon your Spirits. You like it as a <hi>Refuge from Hell:</hi> But can you ſavour it, and take any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it under this conſideration, as a place where you ſhall <hi>be for ever with Chriſt?</hi> You may know this by the ſtanding frame and workings of your Hearts towards him. If your Eyes have not been opened to ſee his Beauty, if your Hearts have not been drawn to him, if your Souls do not pant and thirſt after him, and rejoyce in him; if he be as a wither'd Flower to you, the Heaven which the Goſpel hath propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to us, cannot be grateful to you. How can ſuch a Man tune his Voice to ſing the Song of the Lamb, or take any pleaſure in that place, if it were poſſible for him to crowd into it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. See to it that you be perſons <hi>ſo qualified,</hi> that when you die, you may <hi>be preſent with the Lord.</hi> Suppoſe God ſhould ſay to you, <hi>This night ſhall thy Soul be required of thee,</hi> Whither do you think it would go? Don't many of your Hearts miſgive you, and your guilty Conſciences tell you, not to be with Chriſt, but with Devils and damned Spirits beneath? Die ere long you muſt, and the youngeſt and ſtrongeſt among you know not how ſoon. There's a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Executioner that ſtands inviſibly by us all, and hath not promiſed the Civility to wait till we give the <hi>Sign;</hi> he may ſuddenly and without any warning give us the fatal Blow. It may be in a little while you may be filled with ſuch intolerable Pains, that you may long to be abſent from the Body, that you may be out of your Miſery. But yet how will you be able to wiſh for that, if you are tortured with Fears of hearing thoſe dreadful words, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51645:15"/>
            <p>Will you then <hi>believe on the Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt with all your hearts? For the unbelievers will be ſhut out.</p>
            <p>Will you ſeek after <hi>Regeneration?</hi> For <hi>verily, verily,
<note place="margin">John 3.3.</note> I ſay unto you, Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the kingdom of God.</hi> Give God no reſt till he put this good Principle into you, that you may <hi>ceaſe from evil, and do good.</hi> Without this, the moſt glittering Profeſſion will not avail; and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes will find it ſo when 'tis too late. You have the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription</hi> of God upon you, ſee that his <hi>Image</hi> alſo be ſtamped on your Souls, otherwiſe you will be rejected. Our Saviour in propounding the Parable of the Virgins,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> ſpeaks of them as though there was an <hi>equal</hi> number of wiſe and fooliſh ones, <hi>five</hi> of one ſort, and <hi>five</hi> of the other. But in our days we have reaſon to apprehend the latter do vaſtly exceed the former; and then they will look like <hi>fooliſh</hi> ones indeed, when that Scripture ſhall be fulfilled, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is written,
<note place="margin">Luke 13.26, 27.</note> that the Judge ſhall ſay to many that <hi>have eat and drunk in his preſence, and heard him in their ſtreets, I know not whence you are, Depart from me all ye workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> The Sentence, is Severe, but Righteous, and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal too. All that fall under that Character ſhall fall under that Condemnation; and 'tis worth our while to obſerve the diſdainful manner wherein their Plea is over-ruled, and Execution awarded againſt them. <hi>Then ſhall ye begin to ſay, q. d.</hi> this is ſo idle and frivolous an Allegation in the behalf of the workers of Iniquity, that they <hi>have eat and drunk in my preſence, and I have taught in their ſtreets,</hi> that I can have <hi>no patience</hi> to hear it: I will cut off ſuch fooliſh Babblings and idle Arguments immediately, for they do not deſerve any regard. And <hi>I tell you, I know not whence you are.</hi> I ſcorn to be thought to have any Acquaintance with, or Reſpect for ſo vile a Generation of Men. I often warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them that I would diſown them; and I now judicially declare, I am unalterably fixed, and will never change my mind.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51645:16"/>
            <p>Will you ſerve and imitate the Example of Chriſt? For <hi>if any man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 12.26.</note> ſaith he, <hi>will ſerve me, let him follow me, and where I am there ſhall my ſervant alſo be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that Men were wiſe for themſelves, that they would conſider and prepare for their latter End, that then an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance may be adminiſtred to them into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour!</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let holy Souls <hi>labour after this divine and raiſed frame</hi> of Spirit, to be <hi>willing rather to be abſent from the body,</hi> that they may be <hi>preſent with the Lord.</hi> How willing was Chriſt to come from Heaven, a far better Place than this where we are, to undergo a ſharper Death for you, than you can ſuffer to be with him? And ſhould you be unwilling to depart hence, and go to him? How unkindly may he take ſuch a temper, when he is gone to prepare ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Place for you, that you ſhould be ſo backward to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it? He deſires that you may be <hi>where he is, to behold his glory;</hi> And ſhould not the ſame mind be in you that is in him? What though Death lie in the way? Is it not an Enemy that he hath Conquer'd, and pluck'd out its Sting? What have you in this World, the Element of Sin and Sorrow, whoſe Pleaſures are ſo thin, whoſe Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are ſo weighty, that you ſhould hang about it, and cleave ſo faſt to it? Methinks you ſhould groan earneſtly within your ſelves to be gone to that better Place and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>That you may be willing, draw off your Affections from every thing here below; take heed of over-indulging the Body, and the Pleaſures of it; familiarize Death to your ſelves by ſerious Meditations; encreaſe in the Knowledge of the Myſtery of the Father, and of Chriſt, Faith in him, and love to him; beware of wilful Sins; get and keep your Evidences for Heaven clear, and let the Glory of God and Chriſt be the end of your lives.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51645:16"/>
            <p n="4">4. Let not ſurviving Friends <hi>too much regret and bewail the Death of</hi> their <hi>Holy Relatives.</hi> They are gone from us, but they are with Chriſt, where they were and are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be.</p>
            <p>And this I doubt not is the Caſe of your late Reverend deceaſed Paſtor, Mr. <hi>Richard Mayo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was a Man of ſincere Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>A worthy Perſon,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Single<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
               </note> ſufficiently known in this City for his great Skill and Pains in training up of Youth, was the happy Inſtrument which Providence made uſe of for the firſt awakening and enclining him to look out after God. I have often heard him ſpeak with great thankfulneſs both to God and him, of that mixture of Love and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence whereby he gained upon him.</p>
            <p>God having engraven a Divine Image upon his Heart, uſed him as a <hi>Seal</hi> to impreſs the ſame upon many others. For upon this he ſoon entred (tho Young) upon the Sacred Work of the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not follow him into all the places of his Abode, tho he was like a Box of ſweet <hi>Perfume,</hi> that ſheds abroad a fragrant Smell whitherſoever 'tis carried and open'd. It ſhall ſuffice to take notice of one or two only.</p>
            <p>He was fixed for many years at <hi>Kingſton upon Thames,</hi> where he had a large opportunity for Service, and his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours were crowned with an anſwerable Succeſs. And tho moſt of the old Diſciples that were wont to ſit under his Miniſtry are dead, yet his Name and Memory ſtill <hi>lives,</hi> and is very precious there to this day.</p>
            <p>But tho that was the place of his ſtated Reſidence, yet he was not confined to it, and 'twas pity he ſhould. He kept up for ſeveral Years, a weekly Lecture in <hi>London</hi> at <hi>White-Chappel Church,</hi> where multitudes flocked after him to that degree, that many were wont to hang about the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51645:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Windows, glad to fix their Foot in any place where they might but have the advantage of hearing him; ſo that they <hi>darkned</hi> as well as <hi>filled</hi> the place. And ſeeing the Multitude, he was moved with Compaſſion, open'd his Mouth and taught them with great Life and Zeal, a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Spirit being pour'd out on him and them, ſo that the Word of the Lord ran and was glorified. Such a deep tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture and ſavour of God, Chriſt, and Religion, was by his means left on the Spirits of many, as is not worn out to this very day.</p>
            <p>At length came that <hi>Black day,</hi> wherein ſo many hundred faithful and excellent Miniſters of Chriſt were ejected; and he among the reſt. But yet they could not wholly ſilence him,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.16.</note> becauſe he remembred that it was written, <hi>Wo be unto me, if I Preach not the Goſpel.</hi> I paſs over all the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing time, which he with the reſt of his Brethren ſpent with a great variety of interchangeable Providences till he came to be fixed with you.</p>
            <p>You know his preaching among you to have been ſolid, weighty, and ſubſtantial, apt at once to inſtruct and move. For the matter of it, it was things of the greateſt importance, Chriſt crucified, the neceſſity of an Intereſt in him, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and Obedience to him; imputed Righteouſneſs and inherent too, not putting one into the room, or exalting it to the Prejudice of the other, both being neceſſary in their proper places, and to diſtinct ends, which he knew well how to aſſign, and warmly to preſs. Three great Excellencies in his Preaching I have often obſerved, that it was methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, clear, and genuinely derived from his Text, like ripe and fair fruit that drops from the Bough whereon it <hi>naturally</hi> grew. I had rather that your <hi>Lives</hi> than my Tongue or Pen, ſhould ſhew how ſucceſsful his Labours have been among you; yet I have had the opportunity of knowing that here he hath been far from labouring in vain; tho it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51645:17"/>can't be preſumed, but that he hath done a great deal more good than ever came to my knowledge, or even to his own, while he was here below.</p>
            <p>As for his great inſight into Divinity, both Polemical and Practical, his Learning and Ingenuity, you may have a taſt of all theſe if you peruſe what he himſelf hath publiſht; a Catalogue of which you will find annexed to the end of this Diſcourſe. And indeed Men's own Books are far better <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures</hi> of the Authors, than any of thoſe which their Friends are ſometimes pleaſed to ſet before them. We may in theſe Points more fully and exactly diſcern what manner of Men they are, by what they themſelves have written, than by any Repreſentations that another can make of them. The Underſtanding Reader may become more ſo, by a diligent conſulting of what he hath printed; and then will have reaſon to thank me, tho I only do the Office of <hi>a hand in the Margent,</hi> point out to him thoſe remarkable things that deſerve a very attentive peruſal.</p>
            <p>Beſides all this, he had ſome other moſt valuable Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications; ſuch as a great love for Peace and Union. This he unweariedly purſued with a godly Zeal in deſpight of all Diſcouragements; a thing that all wiſe and good Men can't but wiſh to ſee effected for the Glory of God, and the publick Welfare. For Animoſities and Diviſions, ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Anger and Paſſion in the Boſoms of Brethren one againſt another, will naturally <hi>produce</hi> as many terrible Effects, as blazing Comets in the Heavens are generally thought to <hi>preſage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Add to all this his great Sincerity, and an excellent Sweetneſs of a natural Temper that ran through his whole Converſe, like a Golden Thread through a Garment.</p>
            <p>With ſuch a one you may be ſure that I could not but lead a very happy and comfortable Life. We drew in the ſame Yoke, and the ſame Way, though indeed on my ſide with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51645:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>a <hi>vaſtly unequal ſtrength.</hi> He treated me with the ſame gentleneſs and kindneſs as the <hi>right</hi> hand doth the <hi>left. The pleaſure of a Miniſter's Life and the ſucceſs of his Labours greatly depend on this; the contrary will weaken his Hands, and is enough to break his very Heart. Where two are joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſerve their common Lord in one place, though matters ſhould not come to an open Breach and Quarrel, yet if there be but a ſhineſs, or a ſecret diſpleaſure againſt each other tainting their Spirits; or if there be but</hi> oblique <hi>Reflections, 'tis like the two Eyes in a Man's Head turned ſeveral ways and looking ill-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouredly on each other, a very unpleaſant and uncomely thing, and very prejudicial to the Body which they are to ſerve:</hi> But God be thanked it was not ſo with us. We have lived and laboured together among you for about the ſpace of eight Years, and matters have been carried with the ſame endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Affection on his part, and the ſame reverential Reſpect on mine, as are wont to be between a Father and a Son; which have been ſo far from decaying, that they were daily on the growing hand: Like the <hi>Joynts</hi> of the Body the longer we grew, the more firmly we were knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; of which he gave me very ample Proofs, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly throughout his late Sickneſs, which put a period to his Days about the 65th Year of his Age.</p>
            <p>His make and the ſtrength of his Conſtitution, and his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted ſtate of Health for ſo many Years (which made his Life like a ſtrong Thread drawn out to a great length without any <hi>Knots</hi>) promiſed a much longer continuance here. And could the Skill of his <hi>Eminent Phyſicians,</hi> who were alſo his cordial Friends, have effected it, we had ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enjoyed him. But experience ſhews us, that neither the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Strength of the Place, nor all the contrivances of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt excellent Artiſts, are able to keep a Caſtle from being taken, which is ſtrongly beſieged by a numerous and poten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Enemy, and furiouſly battered by a great train of Artillery.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:51645:18"/>
            <p>He was attack'd by a great variety of Diſtempers; and while endeavours were uſing to diſmount one Battery, another as ſtrong and threatning was raiſed; and then no wonder the Fortreſs was ſo ſpeedily taken, even tho the Gariſon had not been weakned by any foregoing Siege. But there was no Diſtemper in his Mind, tho ſo many in his Body; his <hi>Soul</hi> was in <hi>health</hi> and at eaſe. Through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole of his Sickneſs of ſix Weeks continuance, all was clear between God and him. His end was like the <hi>Light</hi> of the Evening when the <hi>Sun</hi> ſetteth,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.4.</note> an Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>without any Clouds.</hi> He ſaid to my ſelf, when I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him, concerning that matter, <hi>I have not indeed thoſe raptures of Joy which ſome have felt, (tho yet,</hi> he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>bleſſed be God, I have ſometimes taſted of them too) but I have a comfortable well-grounded hope of Eternal Life.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, <hi>I have had my Infirmities and Failings; but my heart hath been right with God as to the main, and I look for the Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt to Eternal Life.</hi> Again, another time, <hi>I know that I have paſſed from Death to Life.</hi> And again, <hi>Bleſſed be God for our Lord Jeſus Chriſt who hath delivered me from the wrath to come.</hi> In the preſence of others that ſtood by him, when the ſudden <hi>Blaſt</hi> was ſo ſtrong as almoſt to puff out the Lamp of Life, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to dye in a very few moments, he ſaid in the words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Into thy hands I commit my Spirit; thou haſt redeemed me, O Lord God of truth;</hi> and this was utter'd by him with a more than ordinary chearfulneſs viſibly ſpread on his Face. He would often ſay in his Sickneſs, <hi>If God hath any pleaſure in me, and any more work for me to do, he will raiſe me up; but if not, lo, here am I, let him do with his ſervant what ſeemeth him good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, I could neither obſerve my ſelf, nor learn from thoſe that were conſtantly about him (<hi>who muſt know this matter better than any others,</hi> and would not <hi>lye for God</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51645:19"/>himſelf) that he had the <hi>leaſt Darkneſs</hi> upon his ſpirit as to his preſent and future State from the beginning of his Sickneſs, till he gave up the Ghoſt, which he did the laſt Lords-day about five in the Morning, the time when he was wont to ariſe and prepare himſelf for his Sacred Work. Then did he enter upon his Everlaſting Sabbath, to the very great loſs of his own Family, of this Society in particular, and indeed of the Church of God, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Chriſt in general among us. To our great loſs, but his own gain; and therefore weep not as thoſe that are without hope or comfort. For he is entred into the Joy of his Lord; he is gone within the Vail, and hath left the People weeping without, to whom he ſhall never return. For the Eye that ſaw him in this place with ſo much delight, ſhall ſee him here no more; the Ear that ſo often heard him with pleaſure, ſhall hear his Voice no more.</p>
            <p>But tho the <hi>Sower</hi> be dead, let not the <hi>Seed</hi> be ſo. Let me beſpeak you in the words of the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>Remember him that had the rule over you, Who</hi> ſo often <hi>ſpake to you the word of God, whoſe faith follow, conſidering the end of his converſation.</hi> For his END was PEACE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The God of all Grace enable us to prepare to follow, that when our turn ſhall come, we may alſo go to the great Shepherd of the Sheep, even that Jeſus who hath loved us, and waſht us from our Sins in his own Blood, and may be for ever with him ſinging Hallelujahs to God, and to the Lamb that ſitteth upon the Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51645:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>publiſhed by the late Reverend Mr.</hi> Richard Mayo.</head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or a Plain Anſwer to this Practical Queſtion, <hi>What courſe may a Chriſtian take to have his heart quickned and enlarged in the the Duty of</hi> Secret Prayer?</p>
            <p>A Sermon ſhewing, That <hi>the Papiſts dangerouſly corrupt Holy Worſhip by their ſinful Prayers to Saints and Angels.</hi> In the Morning Exerciſe againſt Popery.</p>
            <p>A Sermon ſhewing, <hi>What we muſt do to prevent and cure Spiritual Pride.</hi> In the Continuation of the Practical Morning Exerciſe. Vol. 3.</p>
            <p>A Sermon ſhewing, <hi>From what Fear of Death are the Children of God delivered by Chriſt, and by what means doth he deliver them from it.</hi> In the Caſuiſtical Morning Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes. Vol. 4.</p>
            <p>The Life and Death of Dr. <hi>Staunton.</hi> To which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Doctor's Treatiſe of Chriſtian Conference. And his Dialogue betwixt a Miniſter and a Stranger.</p>
            <p>Two Conferences. One betwixt a Papiſt and a Jew. The other betwixt a Proteſtant and a Jew. In Two Letters from a Merchant in <hi>London</hi> to his Correſpondent in <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Letter from <hi>Leghorn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Comment on the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans.</hi> In the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Volume of Mr. <hi>Pool's Engliſh</hi> Annotations.</p>
            <p>The Cauſe and Cure of Strife and Diviſions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51645:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS Printed for</hi> Thomas Cockerill, <hi>at the</hi> Three Legs <hi>in the</hi> Poultrey.</head>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Right Honourable Sir <hi>John Shorter,</hi> Lord Mayor of <hi>London.</hi> By <hi>Nath. Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon of the Inſtrumentality of Faith. And a Sermon upon the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. Both by <hi>W. Croſs,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>A Sermon at the Funeral of Dr. <hi>Jeremiah Butt.</hi> By <hi>Ed. Veal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Infant Baptiſm God's Ordinance. By <hi>Michael Harriſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon at the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>Lobb</hi> late Wife of Mr. <hi>Stephen Lobb.</hi> By <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Slater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God the Guide of Youth. A Sermon Preached by <hi>T. Cruſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſtructions about Heart-Work, what is to be done on God's part and ours, for the cure and keeping the Heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By that Eminent Goſpel Miniſter Mr. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Alleyn.</hi> With a Preface by Dr. <hi>Anneſley.</hi> The 2d Edition.</p>
            <p>The Evidence of Things not ſeen: Or divers Spiritual and Philoſophical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, concerning the ſtate of Holy Men after Death. By that Eminently learned Divine <hi>Moſes Amyraldus.</hi> Tranſlated out of the <hi>French</hi> Tongue by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Chriſtian Religion in ſundry points, Preached at the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Lecture. By <hi>Tho Cole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning trouble of Mind and the diſeaſe of Melancholly, in three Parts; written for the uſe of ſuch as are or have been exerciſed by the ſame. By <hi>Tim. Rogers,</hi> M A. who was long afflicted with both. To which is added ſome Letters from ſeveral Divines, relating to the ſame Subject.</p>
            <p>Love to Chriſt neceſſary for all to eſcape the Curſe at his coming. By <hi>Tho. Doolittle,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>An Expoſition of the Aſſemblies Shorter Catechiſm, with Practical Inferences from each Queſtion. By <hi>John Flavell</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Dartmouth</hi> in <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of ſecret Prayer, firſt Preached and now Publiſhed at the requeſt of thoſe that heard it. By <hi>Samuel Slater</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The future State; or a Diſcourſe attempting ſome diſplay of the Souls Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in regard to that eternally progreſſive Knowledge, or eternal increaſe of Knowledge, and the conſequences of it, which is among the bleſſed in Heaven. By a Countrey Gentleman, a Worſhipper of God in the way of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 10. l. <hi>antep.</hi> r. <hi>is as.</hi> p. 14. l. 5. for <hi>Gods</hi> r. <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51645:20"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
